so this is our second podcast and again
we're going to kind of talk about Jordan
Peterson because I think increasingly
he's becoming this kind of lightning rod
for the culture wars like he's he has
become the paradox that we talked about
before like a man who's talking about
overcoming polarization and speaking to
people you don't agree with he's
becoming the most polarizing figure
probably in the world certainly in the
intellectual world right now and it's a
fascinating phenomena in its own right
and it's also just I think works as a
kind of lens to look at a lot of deeper
social dynamics yeah I know I agree and
I think the last week or two was since
the last podcast came out I've been
almost a microcosm and maybe even a
speeding up of that dynamic and Peterson
maybe taking on a different cultural
role so as a journalist thing would be
interesting to hear from you in terms of
obviously there was a New York Times
article and there was the PC debate as
well with with Stephen Fry and others
starting with New York Times article and
the response to it from a journalist
point of view first off what do you make
of that
my sense is reading it was one most of
the more his own words it was a very
friend of mine said it wasn't a hatchet
job it was a stiletto job which I
thought was a brilliant way of putting
it because it was all just very subtly
done and it was and the irony was and I
do think like so far I think Peterson
has been quite lucky and his choice of
opponents like the Kathy Newman
interview Channel four put up the whole
new whole interview unedited he he came
out that interview thinking well they're
going to cut this up and it's going to
make me look terrible they put the whole
thing up when he was shocked and
speaking of someone who used to work for
news I don't think they real
what they were doing when they put that
up there and I think if they could have
taken it down they probably would have
done but that worked in his favor
I'm not converting and I think it might
be quite easy within sort of his bubble
and the bubble of the sort of Peters and
fans of which obviously I'm kind of I am
one but I'd like to try and think I like
to think that as a journalist I should
I'm able to kind of look at the bigger
picture and see both sides I think that
one has done serious damage because I
think what it's done is crystallized
views on both sides the reaction I saw
afterwards on Twitter and the reaction
that I saw afterwards on social media
was gleeful on one side look we told you
this guy was a misogynist we told you he
was regressive and this proves it and so
it's interesting I think to look at
what's behind the polarization and I
even think the term Peterson fans is
interesting every time I hear it I kind
of have a bit of a twinge of like what
because you know I see myself as a fan
of the truth you know and I think a lot
of people who who are you know deeply
inquiring into ideas would probably see
the same thing and Peterson is popular
because he's been speaking an awful lot
of truth where do you think the
polarization is coming from what the
left is hearing with Peterson is there
are these biological realities there are
these things and that means these things
are fated to be the case male and female
gender roles are fated to be the case
these things are fated to be the case
this is what they're hearing from him
and that's the huge reaction because
it's like are we going to have to roll
back to the 1950s I don't think that I I
don't think that's the natural
conclusion of what Peterson is saying
what Peterson is saying is there are
certain immutable truths about our
biological existence that we need to
acknowledge I was in Austin at the voice
and exit festival and Brett Weinstein
was there and hear in his talk he said
we're we understand that we are not
blank slates and for a long time the
left was hoping that we are blank slates
because then we can create them we can
create the world that we want and no no
restrictions and we just socially
engineer it until we've got
perfect world and that's what the left
wants to believe not true clearly not
true but Bret said we may not be blank
slates but we are the blankest slates
around because we're adaptive because we
we are as successful as we are because
we were able to be adaptive so biology
is not fate and this is a key point that
I think can get us to the other side of
this polarization at the moment you've
got the left effectively freaking out
over what they're hearing from Peterson
about like biological realities and all
of this stuff and I think this is a
problem I think Peterson is not helping
because he is not making that case
clearly and I don't know if he believes
that or not I genuinely don't know if he
does actually think everything since the
60s men and women working together all
of this stuff might be an error might be
an experiment that can't work and and we
will end badly so if he is being
misunderstood that's partly his fault
for not sketching out that actually
there is a place on the other side of
this which is we recognize the fact that
we have a biological reality we
recognize our evolutionary heritage we
recognise that men and women have
different skills and adaptations to the
world yet we can use this toolkit to do
something different and as it's another
taking another sort of line out of Bret
Weinstein's thinking if we don't evolve
past the toolkit we've been given by
evolution we are going to extinguish
ourselves because also in that toolkit
is hardwired tribalism
and we're seeing that we're seeing that
play out like the social media has made
all of this worse we are seeing all of
these sort of different temperamental
camps pulling into like isolation and as
Jordan Greenhalgh said this is an
extinction Airy level threat that we're
now in armed camps around each other and
everyone's kind of picking up on this in
this polarization but there is and
Peterson unwittingly is feeding into
that polarization because he is not
making that other leap beyond yes there
is
scientific reality that everyone that is
not that he's in disputed in the
scientific literature it's only the sort
of bias of the of the mainstream media
that kind of doesn't believe or doesn't
want to accept all this stuff but he is
not pointing to the deeper resolution
and that is crucial and it's like it's
like this idea of reviving your father
from the underworld which is a central
mythological idea it's like we have to
re discover and reanimate the essential
truths of our culture that's what he's
saying like the logos lived out truth
aligning oneself with the truth all of
that stuff but that's gonna look very
different now than it did in prehistory
that resolution we're not going back to
men and women in in completely separate
spaces and all that stuff we've started
an experiment in the 60s that we're
going to have to see through but we're
only gonna be able to see it through and
I think a lot of this underpins like the
gender dynamics and the problems with me
too and the way that men and women are
kind of also polarizing is to recognize
that polarity and recognize that reality
and then say and we move through we move
through it we recognize that we have
different experience of the world but
and we're not equality doesn't mean
equivalence
it doesn't mean sameness we can reclaim
polarity but we can reclaim in a
conscious way that doesn't put one over
the other it doesn't it doesn't mean
that men and men are superior to women
or any of the stuff that that a kind of
that has been part of our kind of
heritage yeah I find this absolutely
fascinating this this concept coming out
of evolutionary biology about your genes
effectively having their own agenda
self-replicating themselves being you
know selfish so to speak and you know
hearing Brett von Stein talk about it it
mediately made me think in terms of kind
of a global solution and that next step
it is like the way the ego can be
conceived of phenomenologically when you
do inner work and it's what you know
Eastern traditions have been talking
about for a long time when you look at
yourself and inquire into yourself
there is there is an ego there which is
in a sense a kind of a machine that is
designed to help you survive in the
world self-replicating machine it's got
all of these drives that have very
little to do with you very much so yeah
and then not which also kind of maps on
to the shadow idea as well yeah but the
idea that we have these kind of programs
that want the DOM and I want to control
want to kind of to fight we need to
integrate those yeah and the mistake
what we normally try and do is suppress
them that's what makes a shadow it's
like oh I don't have that violent
tribalism in me ama and a good boy it's
effectively where it comes from and
that's exactly it it leaks down you
start projecting it outward and you
could argue that racism and anagen has
argued this racism is the ultimate
explanation of the shadow you know see
the ultimate way of seeing the shadow
it's like the other nests within
yourself and everything you hate about
yourself gets projected on to the the
other and it's a really fascinating
concept because the ego is the object of
the transformation so it's a mistake
also to try and kind of kill your ego
because you need your ego what you do is
do transform your ego by taking a step
back and looking at it which is very
similar to what Bret Weinstein is
talking about when he talks about not
being the slave to your genes to be
aware of it and go hey you know what I
don't want to kill or be killed I don't
want X Y Zed I'm going to be I think in
a video releasing it cause it the
captain of my own ship this is my
airplane you know which it takes from
the movie Sully this is my airplane and
that is crucial and the only way in my
opinion to get there is to really look
at yourself and know how to do that and
enter these states where you can really
delve in and enquire and ideally doing
that on a collective level or at least
enough of enough people doing it is
there something we touched on this in
the last podcast but it's effectively
this inability to recognize that we all
have this tribalism is what's created
the reaction of a brexit and Trump like
this liberal this liberal idea of where
the good guys we're tolerant part from
those people who don't think like us and
that's that's what we're seeing at the
moment it's like this shadow and
it's so easy to persuade oneself that we
don't have a shadow we are the good
people we are and and that because it's
it's coming from a deeper place it's
coming from this kind of it's like how
in alignment is is your is your set of
beliefs and your set of motivations and
your set of not motivators but your your
kind of intellectual center and your
kind of reactivity Center because it's
very rare in this world to find people
who have both in alignment we've driven
by things we don't we barely recognize
as the whole kind of psychoanalytic
insight is that we're not masters of our
own house as again Peterson talks about
and it's the other thing I want to kind
of talk about as well is that this the
IDW the intellectual darkweb concept so
it was named by the New York Times a
couple of weeks ago I think even that
has the danger of becoming another
tribalism because the reaction to the
New York Times article I saw ben shapiro
put out this really sort of castigating
piece i mean quite rightly though the
journalist had an agenda and it was
though there was a lot to take on there
but it's very easy for even the people
in in this sort of intellectual dark web
movement of which apparently we are on
the outskirts or according to the
website that's identified us as critical
darker web which maybe means we're
allowed to criticize I don't know like
that can become another tribalism very
easily because the whole idea I think
for me if if the intellectual dial-up is
to become a genuine thing and a genuine
force has to be that there's some sense
of I mean it is it is not homogeneous
it's supposed to be heterogeneous -
that's the whole point is that people
don't necessarily agree but they are
they agree to be able to have
conversations so I think it's important
that people disagree with in it or are
allowed to disagree within it so I would
criticize or at least question Peterson
around a couple of things one of which
is this is this not seeing the place
beyond the polarization and I think also
the
way and I can completely understand this
he's under unfair attack all the time so
he would have to be superhuman to not
react in some way to that and he clearly
reacts and you see him on Twitter you
see him I know of people who I think
would be won over by his message who
followed him on Twitter and stopped
following because they're like this he's
an angry he's an angry guy and I know
there was an even a in an article quite
recently I know he's been told if
Twitter Peterson keeps coming out then
that's the end that's the end of it and
and you saw that in the debate just the
other day in the free speech the monk
free speech debates he was angry he was
tetchy he he I mean he was again I'm
completely unfairly attacked the guy on
the other side said you're a you're a
mean white man it's like I'm Peterson I
thought the words that he used he dealt
with it really well he said okay can
call me mean maybe I mean I'm probably
no more mean than many other people but
why did you have to bring race into it
which I think's absolutely right like
why did you bring race into it how would
it have been if that if it had been
reversed I mean it's just that that's
the the problem with identity politics
all the way through is like it is
essentially a divisive force pitting one
group against another it's it's
catastrophic
but you saw Stephen Fry just dealing
with it with a level of wit and
lightness of touch and humor but
firmness and you just thought wow this
is what it takes to get the other side a
bit of humor a bit of lightness and
Stephen Fry actually said he used the G
K Chesterton quote angels can fly
because they take themselves so lightly
which is a fantastic way of looking at
it and as I said this is I am
criticizing this I'd like for things
this is constructive criticized because
I because I think it would be almost
impossible for Peterson to have reacted
in any other way if you look at the
trajectory that he's gone through over
the last few months the kind of levels
of unfair criticism the the way that
he's kind of come from
nowhere to being this kind of
Centrepointe in in the public discussion
it's almost impossible for anyone to
ground themselves under that kind of
projection and that kind of pressure and
that kind of so I don't yeah I want I
want to sort of frame it in these are
the these are where I see is blind spots
and if while I'm on this I'd also say I
think he still kind of focused on a kind
of student politics thing that there are
other things that he could talk about
like implicit in his work is the idea of
that materialism is a doctrine the idea
of only seeing the world has made up of
material things has been a great
impoverishment because we're not seeing
ourselves as fully human and this is
what we're seeing cascading through our
culture and I think if we started
emphasizing that rather than just
emphasizing the dangers of SJW culture
and all this stuff which is also true
then suddenly I think people would be
saying okay maybe he is an ally because
I think he is an ally I think I think
he's an ally for the left as well as the
right but at the moment he's he's only
being seen as an ally for the right
because of his concentration on the
excesses of campus culture and SJW
culture but actually I think he I think
implicit in a lot of ways saying is it's
stuff that the left is concerned about
as well he just has a different take on
it like in a quote he talks about
inequality it's a huge problem but it's
a much bigger problem and the left
realizes because it's built into almost
every system and we have to be able to
deal with it so there's an integration
like he needs to be integrated and the
reactivity to him almost without fail
I've found shows something that has not
been integrated in the person who's
reacting there's an MV or there's
there's an MB of his success or there's
a inability to see him clearly or
whatever so most of it is reactivity but
there is also if we can integrate what
he say is a culture like this deep
history of West of Western thought that
is not only Western thought
it precedes Western thought it goes back
to Mesopotamia integrates all of these
other kind of much deeper wisdom
traditions integrate that and move
beyond I think we need to move beyond in
but we need to integrate him first and
IV I don't see many people able to
integrate what he's saying and this is
this is also a very interesting point
you're raising I think so to get back to
what you said about Stephen Fry and
about the way Stephen Fry talked and
that kind of lightness I've thought over
the last couple of weeks that what's
interesting is that you know in therapy
it's very important to resource people
to make them feel safe in order for them
to look at the parts of themselves that
they need to look at to to resolve a
trauma or whatever it might be and when
they're in the Paris when they're in the
sympathetic nervous system mode in
fight-or-flight mode which is where
reactivity often comes from it is very
very difficult / impossible to get
someone to change their mind about
anything so you need to get them
resourced which is kind of what Stephen
Fry is doing he's creating a safety by
being like hey let's not take it too
seriously like you know and there's a
lightness and so that is I think you
pull out of the conflict and the the if
your goal really is to move beyond
polarization and move towards a kind of
yes and even if you disagree with
someone then I think that's really
important and I have absolutely no doubt
that Peterson can do that extremely well
with you know two or decades of clinical
practice I just think it's probably
extremely difficult or impossible to do
it with thousands of people shouting at
you every day you know on both sides I'm
telling you you're the best thing since
sliced bread and that you're a fascist
yeah and and so we're Stephen Fry
probably naturally does it is because he
is a performer and and a very witty man
as well he is a performer and there is
and so the irony of what I'm about to
say is that for all of the left's
focused on tonality in the way people
communicate things there is something to
be gained from that because the way you
say something doesn't change the
intellectual merit or the logic of what
you're saying
but it certainly changes how it's going
to be received but it also does change
what you're saying how's the fire
because if I say hello or I say hello
yeah those are two different things
those are two different things I mean
the idea like the medium is the message
it's the idea that this kind of bizarre
slightly autistic often male insistence
on no it's just the fact it's like no
it's not just the facts it's like the
way that you say something communicates
almost more than the stuff that you're
saying so there's this kind of bizarre
insistence and you see it a lot I get
into a lot of those arguments online
where someone is saying you won't engage
with what I'm saying it's like it's
because the way you're doing it shows
that one your wedded to a position that
means there's no point in me engaging
with you
because you're just trying to prove
yourself right why would I get involved
in a conversation with someone who's
just trying to prove themselves right
and I can pick that up from the
emotional charge with which you're
coming forward I'm thinking of someone
in particular I won't mention their name
but because he's so obsessed with me
he's gonna watch this and yeah but it's
like if you're coming with this kind of
obsessive quality or then it's like I'm
not what's the point of engaging with
you there's no way you're just it's not
an open inquiry that the conversations
we need to have and that's again coming
back to the whole intellect or darkweb
concept is the conversations we need to
have are beyond reactivity they're
beyond trying to prove ourselves right
they've genuine inquiries into where is
this person coming from what does this
person got to teach me I may not know
something crucial that's and that that's
tied into the emotionality or otherwise
of the way that this is delivered he I
think is gonna have to recognize some of
the reactivity of what he's bringing
because if he doesn't he's going to
continue to like what you what you
resist persists
it's the idea that the force that you're
putting something out into the world
will meet an opposite in equal force by
definition and if he's coming from a
slightly when he's one of the most
integrated guys around like he's really
integrated his shadow he's got his anger
working for him he's got all this stuff
but there is a reactivity and that's why
some not all because I think he would
create polarization anyway but some of
the polarization I think is coming from
that now this is our second podcast
we're introducing a new member of the
rebel wisdom team this is raffia Morgan
who I'll embarrass him by by calling him
the best facilitator I've ever worked
with a very very wise man who is going
to give us some of his wisdom see what
comes we've concentrated at all on
Jordan Peterson because for me what he
symbolizes is the potential
reintegration of the sacred into a
society that I think have really lost
its way in this kind of materialism and
its kind of as Qatar
cut us off from a really deep part of
ourselves the religious the mythological
the spiritual all these sort of ways
that we yeah we used to make sense of
the world and I think speak to something
really deep in ourselves and the this is
yeah what was your foot your first
thoughts when you encounter Peterson I
mean we're going to go on to because at
the moment we were kind of reflecting on
where his blind spots might be but just
to start what what did you get from
Peterson at the beginning what was your
first kind of experience well I started
listening to a lot of quotes which you
are phonetically sending to me and I was
like what there's a really intelligent
voice out there who's addressing some of
the main concerns things that are
affecting my life questions that I've
never been clear about or had
before I felt like I was impressed guys
done his work and and from the sound and
feel of it he's taking the tough path
and that suddenly he had a voice was
kind of exhilarating for me and I really
hoped that he was maybe the the cutting
new cutting edge of a synthesis of a lot
of the stupidity that's been around
forever basically a lot of the
polarization with a right and a left and
the incapacity to talk and that there is
somebody who gets the bigger picture and
can weave this whole thing in a way that
would address you know real-life
concerns for lots and lots of people so
I'm very enthused and I've used quotes
from him in my groups particularly hid
the work that he does and talks about
integrating the shadow I feel has been
had a direct application in my groups
that's saying he articulated extremely
well yeah my sense is that it would be
almost impossible for him not to have
had some kind of the way he's attacked
I mean he's unfairly attacked again and
again and again and again so he would
need to be superhuman not to have some
kind of reactivity to that but I mean we
went to see him at the Hammersmith
Apollo the other day and for the first
half an hour he was kind of railing
against the left and railing against the
people who'd and who'd kind of been
mistreating him and I just it just felt
unnecessary like you've kind of you're
at this kind of intellectual superstar
level right now and and it seems to be
getting to him in a way that is
unnecessary and also I worry is just
creating more of the same polarization
that he's trying to get us past I really
wanted him and really hope that he was
going to represent something that kind
of left the reactivity of the right and
the left behind and started to offer
something that
was just so intelligent and I think he's
capable of it when I sat in the crowd
and when the railings against the left
came they my my respect my energy level
my attention span my enthrall my feeling
of being in the presence of a really
strong intelligence let's say went right
down because there it was there was the
personal stuff that was coming out that
hasn't really been worked through you
know yeah he got screwed on New York New
York Times article was a hit job and he
was he was gonna lose his job for a long
time back last year I mean he's been you
know and he has had to get in and show
him one hand I love that he stands up in
he creates polarity like between
masculine and feminine he talks so
intelligently about that and I think
it's such an important thing to come out
of you know the liberal left you you
know all the post-modern everybody's the
same kind of crowd you've done an awful
lot of kind of work with with this kind
of stuff what happens when you put out
that kind of reactivity what where does
it come from what does it create in the
world well it's always we have to say
everything that I have a strong
emotional reaction to inside myself is
informing me something about myself
personally it's not an objectivity
there's not a clarity there there's a
strong emotional charge so it requires
inquiry why do I have such a big charge
there go into it a little bit come
become a little bit more responsible and
please save us from the blame game
because it just it just immediately
drives things down familiar old canyons
that we know don't work in it's not
what's needed right now we need we need
Jordan to rise to his best and that
means he has to be a little bit more
media savvy sorry he needs to work on
his own stuff like everybody else he can
do it he advocates it and maybe not go
on kind of overly simplistic tours
because I had that feeling when I saw
him
that I was part of even even from the
introduction to the whole thing there
was a it got a little bit contrived to
me I didn't wake up feeling inspired and
I feel inspired by him often
well the bit that really resonated was
the Q&A at the end Q&A felt natural the
delivery of the talk felt like I sort of
told him yeah and it's a shame I mean
there's two things that I would say one
of which is that I feel assured also a
similar kind of disappointment because
he's carrying the hopes and I know I'm
sure he takes this like he realizes this
he's carrying more than his own fair
share the burden like he's carrying the
book he's going to these debates with
sam harris i mean that he's carrying a
sort of flame for this reintegration of
the sacred for this great tradition of
young this great tradition of all of
this stuff that has to be I have no
doubt has to be integrated for us to
move forward we have to get past but
this is kind of naive materialism and
naive scientism that someone that sam
harris represents it's like where
religion is stupid and everyone else is
stupid who doesn't think like it's just
jack come on grow up who the arrogance
of that is just ridiculous yes and he's
carrying this like he's carrying here's
the kind of the hero at the moment for
this this other way of looking at the
world I mean there was a debate that he
did with this guy Matt Dillahunty
though maybe try and show a clip of here
where he pretty much everything that I
saw said that he pretty much lost that
debate and part of it was his body
language he was kind of over like this
and kind of dissed Matt Dillahunty was
leaning back and kind of rare in control
of it and and Peterson was was leaning
only seemed peevish and tetchy and never
quite completed what he was trying to
say and I admire the guy pareve as much
as I've admired certainly anyone in the
public eye for a long time I put up put
in some ways some of my sort of personal
credibility behind supporting him making
the documentaries and and so it's quite
hard to see
that happened I I'm just curious do you
think that he's just bitten off more
than he can chew right now is he is he
trying to spread himself too wide I
think that he maybe has internalized
that he's on a solo mission when he
doesn't need to be on the side of a
mission yes that there are people trying
to do the same thing as he is trying to
do like the idea of rescuing your father
from the belly of the whale the idea
that we have to integrate our culture to
move forward I know a lot of people who
are in the same that same log yeah and
he's gone I mean the impression I got
when I met him in October in his house
was he's come from soccer academia and a
fairly small pond and he's now this kind
of huge figure and and I worry that he
deliberately or not is not taking in the
right advice at the right times and just
seeing that this thing is bigger than
him this thing is he doesn't have to do
it all alone and there are other people
out there who can help with with the
mission that we all kind of in in our
own way like the same mission that we're
on with Weber wisdom it's like this this
is the time this is the time where we
need to integrate all of this stuff
because the way things are going at the
moment the polarization is increasing
there are existential threats and things
feel very fragile this is what we're
doing and rebel wisdom is about
integrating the great ideas but also
integrating the emotional reality
integrating the deeper sort of embodied
reality of what needs to happen because
all of that needs to happen at the same
time it can't just be an intellectual
exercise yeah and of course it tends to
go that way with him by his personality
he seems very very dry I recommended
recently he needed a night together with
us seeing in the backyard bear
yeah just talking and hanging out
I just felt he was he was on edge and I
and up something in me was like sank
inside yeah a little bit I was like he's
burning his pit and they're after him
yeah he's an easy mark right now I felt
that I mean I hope that he is getting
good advice and because I I felt the
same thing I felt for a while that most
of the criticisms of him were unfair and
I still think almost all the criticisms
were here but there is this other level
of you don't look like you're enjoying
it don't look like you're enjoying it
and this is the other thing that also
there's there's kind of I think what I'm
pretty sure that in underneath this like
we've got a lot of Peterson fans who
watch our stuff I reckon some of the
comments will be sort of saying yeah
you're just bringing in like he's just
masculine and you're just bringing in
this sort of feminine touchy-feely stuff
and did it it is which it's like no yeah
people will say that and you know it's
just because you know I know
for us revel wisdom and the way we're
talking and looking at things is we're
doing the work and part of that work is
that we're going in and we're facing our
own shadow sides and we're shape and and
were exchanging our feelings and the
outcome of that is it creates a grounded
sense of masculinity that has feelings
yes men also have feelings hello you
know we do and their their personal and
there are certain collective aspects to
them and they're absolutely necessary
for a communication that's going to be
effective in this world and we always
when we find ourselves in a strong
reaction to something we turn that
inquiry back here because there's always
something inside that's trying to come
to the light come to
earth trying to inform us and I use my
own reactivity all the time to look at
myself it doesn't bring me into a
feminine sprays space it brings me into
a relaxed confident male space and I
just feel Jordan recently it's just
showing some things around the edge
where it feels like he's you know
stopped before you before you burned
down the whole city just because you've
got really reactive about something yeah
you got hurt you're getting hit jobs you
know you're being misunderstood you're
being misinterpreted you're threatening
a cell you're controversial you're right
out on the edge it's gonna come back at
you you know but have someplace where
you go in there and you just don't try
and just out think and in that out
thinking come to some kind of blame
because blame doesn't work blame
registers as a kind of weak response
show up and and show up inside yourself
and and work through that reactivity and
it will make a huge difference in what
comes out of his mouth if he does that
mmm I thought this before it's like he
says it's all implicit in the stuff that
he's talking about the idea that people
don't have ideas ideas have people so
this reactivity to the kind of SJW types
while understandable can we not find
compassion for people who've been kind
of sold a pop in terms of their view of
the world even duped and we yeah
misinformed yeah yeah yeah we can do
that and we can and we can and we can
have a certain compassion for that and
we can show that in a light that doesn't
have to be waving a big torch you know
against something else we need a bigger
vision that is more inclusive and that
is not giving up taking a stand it's
taking a stand for a higher vision that
is more inclusive that is willing to
get the right that is willing to look at
the left that can find some kind of
synthesis out of all that and stand for
that and address the real issues and not
just get lost in the kind of
name-calling polarity stuff that's been
going on forever and it's just so tiring
one last thing I'd like to say which is
I have a sense just having gone back
from America the voice and exit festival
in Austin I don't think they are going
to be able to find that or I think it's
will be very very difficult and to find
that sort of place beyond the polarity
in America because I think everything's
so polarized there so split I have some
hope that that could happen in the UK
that we have more of a of a civility we
have more of the humor which able is
able to kind of diffuse these
conversations and also that we the
talent for the UK is for synthesis like
we're we're very good at synthesis in
New York and comedy and that's the
essence of creativity is taking stuff
from here and stuff from here and stuff
from here and putting it together that's
the essence for the British creativity I
have a hope that that conversation can
happen here and that's what I want
river wisdom to be able to do to be able
to have that conversation hold that
space of beyond the polarization and the
integration of all of the sort of the
other the other stuff at the same time I
hope me to very much and I agree with
you that this is a place of synthesis
and a lot of times the dawning of the
first things in if there's a clear
enough message that comes out from here
it will catch on in the states it's not
like everybody is so in their camps
although I think in general the
polarization is it's really really great
and it's not there so there's a limit to
the create creative kind of exchange
that can happen everybody reverts to
camp so you've just flown in literally
out of a two hours ago and landed in
London from Austin Texas from the voice
and exit festival and we have a lot of
really great content coming up for
that so what what was the festival like
who did you interview how was it so the
voice and exit festival styles itself as
burning man meets Ted which is true it
was the the production the the whole
thing around that was brilliant like it
was really really well put together so a
lot of kind of techno utopianism
blockchain stuff like that which I am
less interested in like I feel there's a
kind of utopianism that doesn't really
recognize the shadow and doesn't really
recognize some deeper integration but
also they had the other side of it as
well
Bret Weinstein was there Jamie wheel was
there this sort of flow consultant and
we've got some fantastic interviews with
both of them coming up and yeah feels
like yeah it feels like we this is this
is kind of what we're trying to do with
rebel wisdom it's like we've we've done
we've had a big focus on Peterson
because I think what he's bringing
forward is a huge huge value and I also
want to kind of expand and say these are
the other people at Peterson's holding a
big part of a really important puzzle
and there's other people in the
intellectual dark web for example
they're holding other parts of that
puzzle and those people like Jamie wheel
who is holding their like embodied
transformational flow state side of that
puzzle and I really yeah as we go
forward
that's why we're running the events as
well as that we're trying to give people
those experiences of those flow States
and those transformational experiences
and so this is we're trying to give this
with a 360 degree experience of where we
need to go individually and collectively
and culturally
you